是, 大臣  第1季第6集
知情权利
伯纳 大臣还没来吗?
Bernard. Minister not in yet?
来了 他在办公室里开会
He's in his office,having a meeting.
什么会?
What about?
没什么重要的
Nothing very important.
这样啊
I see.
昨天开的是什么会?
And whatwas that meetingin there yesterday?
大臣在审查资料报告程序
He was just reviewingprocedures for briefing him
关于议会质询的
on answersto Parliamentary questions.
但是部门负责人 秘书和下属都出席了
But there were Principals presentand other assorted underlings.
只是为他组织材料的人 汉弗莱爵士
Just the ones who supply himwith the information, actually.
伯纳 这种事得马上停止
Bernard, this has to be stoppedat once.
为什么?
Why?
如果他和下属交谈上了 他不就比我们超前了
Lfhe talks to the underlings,he may learn things we don't know.
完全动摇我们的地位      如果我们能增长知识...
Ourposition could be undermined.If it increases ourknowledge...
增长知识不值得以权威为代价
It is folly if it's at the expenseof your authority.
为什么?
Why?
伯纳 请别问为什么了
Bernard, please stop saying why.
为什么?
Why?
我是说 您能否展开论述一下?
I mean, could you developthat point please?
你觉得大臣开始掌管部门了吗?
Would you say that the Ministeris starting to run the Department?
对 管得还不错
Yes, things are going pretty well,actually.
不 伯纳 当一位大臣亲自掌管部门
No, when a Ministeractuallystarts to run his Department
事情不会"不错"
things are not going pretty well.
只会大错特错
They are actuallygoing prettybadly.
可如今...我说 实际上
But actually... er... I mean, in fact,
管理部门不是大臣的职责么?
isn't it the Minister's jobto run the Department?
不 伯纳 这是我们的职责
No, Bernard, it is ourjob.
准确的说 是我的职责
Orto be more precise,it is my job,
为此我有25年的经验和训练
forwhich I've had 25 yearsexperience and training.
你不知道让大臣来管后果会怎样?
Don't you realise whatwouldhappen if the Ministerruns it?
不知道 怎样?
No, what?
首先 当然会乱成一团
First, there would be chaos,naturally.
第二 更有甚者
And second,which is much more serious,
将会爆发革新
there would be innovations.
改革 伯纳
Changes, Bernard.
公开辩论 流言满天飞
Public debate.Outside scrutiny.
难道你愿意?
Is that what you want?
天啊 当然不要 那他该干什么?
Good heavens, no.But what should he do then?
伯纳 大臣有三项职能
A Ministerhas three functions.
首先 搞推销
First, as an advocate,
让议会和公众接受部里的行动
making the Department's actionsseem plausible
他是我们的公关员
to Parliament and public,he is ourpublic relations man.
其次 他是我们的议会代表
Second, he is ourmanin Westminster,
让我们的立法得以通过
steering our legislationthrough Parliament.
第三 他得养活我们
And third, he is ourbreadwinner.
在内阁争取经费 好让我们
He has to fight in Cabinetforthe money we need
运转我们的部门
to run our Department.
但他不该审查部里的工作程序
But, he is not here to reviewdepartmental procedures
与秘书及下属交流
with Principalsand Assistant Secretaries.
也许他刚好有空      他怎么会有空?
But ifhe's go the time.Why has he got the time?
他不该有空 这是你的错 伯纳
He shouldn't.That's yourfault, Bernard!
你得保证他没有空
You must ensurehe hasn't got the time.
给他找事 伯纳
Create activity, Bernard!
他得去演讲 访问
He should be makingspeeches, visits.
派出代表团 出国考察
We need deputations,junkets abroad,
大批文件盒 得有危机 灾难 险情
mountains of red boxes, we needcrises, emergencies, panics!
振作起来 伯纳      好的 可是...
Pull yourself together, Bernard.Yes, but...
你让他日程表里有空?      不 他安排的
You leave spaces in his diary?No, he makes those.
全部填满      他不允许
Fill them up.He won't let me.
别理他 填满
Don't ask him. Do it.
尽量让他把时间花在无害的地方
Make sure he spends more timewhere he can't do any damage.
哪里呢?      好比说下院
But where?The House of Commons, for instance.
汉弗莱爵士 我真的尽力了 有个代表团在里面
I really do try my best.There's a deputation in there.
什么代表团 伯纳?
What is it about, Bernard?
无关紧要 保护沃里克郡的獾
Somethingcompletely trivial,preserving badgers inWarwickshire.
干得好 伯纳
Well done, Bernard.
怎么不早告诉我?
Why didn't you tell me thiswhen I asked you before?
说实话 我觉得这事太琐碎
Actually, I thoughtitwas rathertrivial.
浪费大臣的时间 我以为您不赞成
I didn't thinkyou would approve, actually.
伯纳
Bernard.
要不要我再去找些濒危动物?
I'll try and find some morethreatened species then, shall I?
远在天边 近在眼前
You may not have to look veryfar.
身为秘书管不住大臣
Secretaries who can't occupy theirMinisters
这就是濒危动物
are a threatened species,
现成的
actually.
您不明白吗 保护自然遗产是我们的神圣使命
We have a sacred trustto preserve ournatural heritage.
可我这项新法的目的就在这里
That's what this new legislationis designed to ensure.
我在下院也说 现有体制行不通
As I said in the House,the system simply isn'tworking.
乱炖一锅
It's a hotchpotch.
地方政府 旅游局
Local authorities,tourist authorities,
国家公园 自治委员会 乡村保护协会
national parks,countryside commision, C.P.R.E.
定位不明 形同虚设
Nobody knows where they are,nothing gets done.
只会互相扯皮 推卸责任
They're all back bitingand buck passing.
那些委员会就是这个样
You knowwhat committees are like.
我们也是委员会啊
We are a committee.
对 我不是说你们这种
Yes. I didn't meanyoursort of committee.
但这项新法旨在统一权责 简化程序
But this new legislation isdesigned to create clearauthority,
节约大笔公共资金
and save a great dealof public money.
你们应该欢迎      那敢情好 可海华树林怎么办?
You ought to welcome it.But what about Hayward's Spinney?
少数小地方会失去保护区地位
Afew very small areas will losetheirspecially protected status,
由于继续保护它们
because it isn't economicalany longer,
不再有经济效益
to maintain themas they ought to.
海华树林是自然遗产的重要组成部分
Hayward's Spinney isa vital part of ourheritage.
獾们祖祖辈辈居住在那里
The badgers have dwelt thereforgenerations.
你确定吗?      《卫报》说的
Can you be sure of that?It said so in The Guardian.
啊 这个...
Ah, well...
确实说獾们祖祖辈辈居住在那里
Actually it says that the badgershave dwelt there forgenerations!
设身处地想
Howwould you feel if you had
你家后院里冒出一片办公楼
a lot of office blocksbuilt overyourgarden
由天外来獾建造 那又怎样?
by a lot of giant badgers?
可一片办公楼...天外来獾?
But a lot of office blocks...giant badgers?
人类没有特权 哈克先生
There's nothing specialabout man, Mr. Hacker.
我们不凌驾于自然之上 我们属于自然
We're not above nature.We're all a part of it.
您知道 人也是兽类
Men are animals too, you know.
我知道 我刚去过下院
Yes, I've just come fromthe House of Commons.
抱歉 大臣 您下个约会快开始了
Sorry, Minister, you are dueforyournext appoinment.
哦 真是遗憾
Oh, what a pity.
谢谢你们这么有力的发言
Thank you forputtingyourcase so persuasively.
幸会幸会
It's been a pleasure.
请从左边走廊下楼梯
Left at the corridorand down the stairs.
但您究竟打算怎么办?
But whatwill you do about it?
届时我们会参考一切观点
All views will be takeninto consideration.
我先失陪了...
Now if you'll excuse me...
您表现太好了 大臣 富有亲和力
Very polished performance.Gracious.
虚晃一枪 多专业啊
And said nothing.Very professional.
怎么没人警告我?      警告什么 大臣?
Why wasn't I warned?About what?
警告我 统一这些管理部门
That unifying the administration
会取消这个海狸什么的保护区?
would remove protected statusfrom this beaverwhatsit?
獾群 大臣 在海华树林 东沃里克郡
Badgercolony. Hayward'sSpinney, East Warwickshire.
一定有人知道
Somebodymust have know about it.
大臣 即使真的有人知道
If somebody did happen to know,
他们未必知道您想知道
they wouldn't necessarily knowthat you wanted to know
他们刚好知道的东西 为此...
what they happened to know,in case...
啊 汉弗莱爵士      汉弗莱
Ah! Sir Humphrey!Humphrey!
早安 大臣
Good morning, Minister.
汉弗莱 难道你的工作是帮大臣丢人现眼?
Is it yourjob to help Ministersmake fools of themselves?
大臣们还真不用我帮忙
I have nevermet onethat needed any help.
不 绝对不是...
No, it is the last thing...
为什么你让我告诉议会和媒体 这个统一法案
Why did you encourage me to saythat unifying the administration
毫无隐患 结果我在给一支
meant no loss of amenity,when I've signed a death warrant
海狸陆战队判死刑?
fora whole army ofbeavers?
是獾 大臣      怎么?
Badgers, Minister.What?
海狸只有海军
Beavers would have a navy.
你怎能让我这样说?      恕我直言 我可没让您说
Why did you let me do it?I did not encourage you to say that.
明明有 部里准备了这个
You did!The Department prepared this.
写着"毫无隐患"      不 大臣
"No loss of amenity", it says.No.
是"毫无重大隐患"      一回事
"No significant loss of amenity".Same thing.
正相反 这区别可大了
There's all the differencein the world.
可以指责任何事"有隐患"
Almost anything can be attackedas a "loss of amenity",
到头来总可以辩解说"毫无重大隐患"
and be defended as"not a significant loss of amenity".
尤其凸显出"重大"一词意义重大
One should appreciatethe significance of"significant".
如果是这样
Well, be that as it may,
任何宣传都危险了
any publicity would bevery damaging.
哦 我看不会 大臣
Oh, I think not.
明明说没隐患 结果造成了隐患
But if there is a loss of amenity...
请过目这份新闻稿 大臣 您会看到
If you'd approve this release,you would see
它能平息所有争论
that it does counterall theirarguments.
里面指出保护区只是取消 没有受威胁
It points out that the spinneyis deregistered, not threatened.
沃里克郡遍地都是獾
Badgers are very plentifulall overWarwickshire.
它同时指出了
And it points out the connection
獾与普鲁士菌病的联系
between Badgersand brucellosis.
以及"不会造成重大隐患" 都在里面
"Cannot be regardedas a significant loss of amenity".
各大媒体不会批评喽?
So this might not getinto the National Press?
《卫报》内页会说几句 不用担心
Afew lines on The Guardian.Nothing to worry about.
实际上 只有城市中产阶级操心
Only the urban middle classworry about
保护乡村的事 他们不用住那里
the preservation of the countryside,because they don't live in it.
还有事吗 大臣?      没了
Would that be all, Minister?Yes!
有 这事算你有理
No, this may well blow over,
但我的基本问题还在
but it doesn't answermy basic question.
什么问题?      为什么我宣布前没听说?
Which was?Why wasn't I told about it?
有人曾经非常中肯地说过
There are those who have arguedand indeed cogently
有必要时 某些事情
that on occasionthere are some things
大臣还是不知道的好
it is betterfora Ministernot to know.
你说什么?
What are you talking about?
大臣 您在议会
Minister, youranswersin the House
和记者招待会上的发言非常得体
and at the Press Conferencewere superb.
掷地有声 令人心悦诚服
You were convincing.The critics were silenced.
但您是否还能这么坚定
But could you have spokenwith the same authority
如果有生态保护组织 在诱您出洞?
if the ecological pressure grouphad been badgering you?
但我有知情权 我是人民的代表
But I have a right to know!I am the people's representative!
你有什么权利把信息藏起来?
What right have you gotto withhold this information?
这是为您着想 大臣      什么叫"还是不知道的好"?
It's in yourown best interests.What do you mean?
无法无天 不能这样下去
It's outrageous!It must not occuragain.
我拟了计划 改组这个部门
I've a plan forthe reorganisingof this Department
保证这种事下不为例
which would ensurethat it doesn't.
真的?      千真万确
Indeed?Yes, indeed.
如果一名副秘书长
If I had one UnderSecretary
和两名助理秘书直接向我报告...
and two Assistant Secretariesreporting to me...
拜托 大臣      听我把计划说完
Minister. Please!Let me tell you my plan.
计划无关紧要
The plan is immaterial.
大臣 我有些话告诉您
Minister, I havesomething to say to you
可能您不爱听
which you may notlike to hear.
哪天你没说过?
Why should today beany different?
大臣 传统的权责分配方式
Minister, the traditional allocationof executive responsabilities
一贯旨在厘清
has always been so determinedas to liberate
大臣职责与行政琐事之分野
the ministerial incumbentfrom the administrative minutiae
通过将管理职能下放
by devolvingthe managerial functions
给那些更有资历
to those whose qualificationshave betterformed them
处理这些琐事的人 从而
forthe performance of suchhumble offices, thereby releasing
让政治领导人投入其地位
theirpolitical overlordsforthe more onerous duties
与职责要求的繁重工作
and deliberations which arethe inevitable concomitant
与深刻思考之中
of theirexalted position.
为什么你觉得我不爱听呢?
What made you thinkI wouldn'twant to hearthat?
我以为会冒犯您
I thought it might upset you.
冒犯什么? 我一个字都没懂
How could it?I didn't understand a single word.
汉弗莱 你就不能说简单点?
Foronce in your life,put it into plain English.
这是您要求的
If you insist.
您不该管部里的工作
You are not hereto run this Department.
你再说一遍?
I beg yourpardon?
您不该管部里的工作
You are not hereto run this Department.
我认为该管 人民也同意
I think I am.The people think I am, too.
恕我直言 大臣 您...他们错了
With respect Minister,you are... they are wrong.
那由谁来管?
And who does runthis Department?
我管
I do.
原来如此
Oh, I see...
那我干什么?      我们谈过这些的
What am I supposed to do?We've been through all this.
制定政策
Make policy.
推动法律生效
Get legislation enacted.
尤其要让内阁保障我们的财政预算
And above all securethe Department's budget in Cabinet.
你就关心财政预算
It seems the budgetis all you care about.
大臣 此事至关重要
It is rather important.
不关心预算 我们部会缩小到
We might end upwith a department so small
连大臣都能管过来了
that even a Ministercould run it.
汉弗莱 我们对民主的本质理解不同吗?
Are we to have a disagreementabout the nature of democracy?
不 大臣 只是分工问题
No, Minister, merelya demarcation dispute.
我是说部里
What I meanis that the menial chore
这些家务事不劳您费心
of running a departmentis beneath you.
您有更崇高的使命
You're fashionedfora noblercalling.
好吧 日常文书工作我交给你
Well, I leavethe routine paperwork to you
但我必须直接获得所有信息
but I must insist on direct accessto all information.
再不许说"有些事情"
Neveragain"There are some things
"大臣还是不知道的好" 明白吗?
it is betterfora Ministernot to know".
不过 大臣      这是命令 汉弗莱
Well, Minister...That is an order, Humphrey!
遵命 大臣 这是您要求的
As you say, Minister.If that is what you really want.
居然把内阁大臣当10岁小毛孩
It's treating Cabinet Ministersas if they were ten yearolds.
午安
Afternoon.
《卫报》看完了 爸?      看完了
Finished with The Guardian?Yes.
抱歉没帮你买《社会主义工人报》
I haven't gotthe Socialist Workerforyou.
你爸看到你下来吃早餐很高兴 对吧?
Daddy's pleased to see you downforbreakfast?
他好久没见你了      我不过睡个懒觉
He hasn't seen you fora while...I was having a lie-in.
总比静坐示威好
Betterthan a sit-in, I suppose.
你昨天怎么回家那么晚?
Why were you so latelast night?
某些事当爸的还是不知道的好
There are some things it's betterfora fathernot to know.
你少来这套
Don't you start!
什么?      没事  没事
What?Nothing, nothing.
我跟"托派"们在一起
I was outwith the Trots.
天
Gosh...
没着凉吧?
Are you going to see a doctor?
托洛茨基分子
The Trotskyites!
哦 你现在信托洛茨基啦?
Oh, a Trotskyite now are you?
不 是彼得
No. Peter is.
彼得?
Peter?
对 彼得
Yes, Peter.
你只见过他15次左右
You've only met himabout 15 times.
哦 就是那个这样...这样...的?
Oh, is he the one with the...and the...
对
Yes.
吉姆 今天我需要你帮忙      什么事?
Jim, I need yourhelp today.Whatwith?
买东西 通水管
Shopping, the kitchen plughole'sblocked,
修理草坪
the lawn needs mowing.
亲爱的 我还有这么多盒重要文件呢      先放着
I've got all these boxes to do.They can wait.
安妮 也许你没发现 我是内阁大臣
Annie, I am a Cabinet Minister.
女王政府的一员
A memberof Her Majesty's Government.
这可是神圣的工作
It's a fairly important job.
但你有2万3千名公务员打下手 我可没有
But you have 23.000 civil servantsto help you, I haven't.
待会再弄备忘录 马上去修水管
Play with yourmemos later,the drains need fixing now.
喂 露西
Oh, Lucy!
果酱都涂到内阁报告上来了
You've got marmaladeall overmy cabinet papers.
我的天
Oh, God.
这下好 黄油也抹上去了 拿抹布来
Now I've got butteron them.Get a cloth.
自己动手      露西
Get it yourself.Lucy.
家里可不是白厅
You're not in Whitehall now.
"是 大臣""当然 大臣""都听您的"
"Yes, Minister", "Certainly","Just as you say".
"能舔您的靴子吗 大臣?"
"May I lick yourboots, Minister?"
露西宝贝 这么说不公平
That's not fair.
公务员对你爸挺恭敬的没错
Those Civil Servants may bealways kowtowing to Daddy,
不过可没把他放在眼里
but they nevertakeany notice ofhim.
告诉你 我刚在部里打了一场胜仗
I've justwon a victoryin my Department.
看看这些盒子
Look at all those boxes.
我就是说这个
That's what I mean.
本来你战胜汉弗莱了 这回又被他压倒了
You were better, now they'vedone a snow job on you again.
绝对没有 这是我要来的      为什么?
Not at all, I asked forall this.Why?
昨天汉弗莱拐弯抹角地说
Humphrey said,"There are some things
"有些事情大臣还是不知道的好"
it's betterfora Ministernot to know".
他对我隐瞒信息 很可能是重要信息
He's witholding things forme,probably important things.
于是我命令他事无巨细都向我报告
So I have insisted that I am toldeverything that goes on.
你到底怎么当上内阁大臣的?
How did you get to bea Cabinet Minister?
真是傻得不透气
You're such a clot.
什么?      还看不出?
What?Don't you see?
你正好上了汉弗莱的当 他肯定高兴坏了
You've playedright into Humphrey's hands.
你主动朝他要来一堆垃圾信息
An open invitation to swamp youwith useless information.
我可不同意
I don't think so.
好吧 都有什么?
What's in that box,for instance?
技术报告 可行性研究
Technical reports,feasibility studies,
各委员会过往记录
past papersof assorted committees,
文具申领单...
stationery requisitions...
活见鬼
Oh, damnation.
赢不了他们 这是个悖论 对不对?
You can'twin.It's Catch 22, isn't it?
信息少了 看不到真相
So little informationyou don't know the facts,
信息多了 又不得要领
orso much you can't find them.
他们就让你原地打转
They've got yougoing and coming.
有篇写你的文章 爸爸      我读过了
There's a story about you here.I've read it.
"屠獾凶手哈克"      你爸读过了 亲爱的
"Hacker, The Badger Butcher".Daddy's read it.
讲什么的?      全是胡话
What's all this then?Lot of rubbish.
"哈克承认取消海华树林的"
"Hackeradmitted that removingprotected status
"保护区资格会导致獾群覆灭"
from Hayward's Spinney meanthe end of the badgercolony".
"英国动物保护组织发言人称"
"A spokesman forthe Preservationof British Wildlife said:
"哈克给獾判了死刑"
"Hackerhas signedthe badger's death warrant".
第一 我不是什么屠凶...屠獾手
One: I am not a babgerb...badgerbutcher...
管他是什么
Whatever it is.
第二 獾不是濒危种族
Two: Badgers are notan endangered species.
第三 取消保护区资格
Three: The removalof protected status
并不是要枪毙所有的獾
does not meanall the badgers will be shot.
第四 就算牺牲几只獾 那也是
And four: If a fewbadgersdie forthe sake
为了保护英国自然遗产的宏伟目标 完毕
of a masterplan thatwill saveBritain's natural heritage, tough.
宏伟目标啊 元首阁下
A masterplan, mein Fhrer.
为达目的不择手段吗?      露西...
The end justifies the means?Lucy...
不就欺负獾们不能投票吗
It's because badgers can't vote.
要是獾有投票权 你才不会消灭它们
Lfbadgers had votes, youwouldn't be exterminating them.
你会在树林里握它们爪子 抱它们崽子
You'd be at Hayward's Spinney,shaking paws, and kissing cubs...
像对选民一样拍他们马屁
Ingratiating yourselfthe way you always do.
露西 别没大没小的      是真的 对吧?
Not a nice thing to say.It's true, isn't it?
对 可你爸是政客 政客就是拍马屁的嘛
Yes, but Daddy's in politics.He has to be ingratiating.
多谢了 亲爱的      不能这样下去
Thank you very much.It's got to be stopped.
晚了 已经决议了      我来阻止它
The decision has been taken.I'm going to stop it.
好办 先提名当候选人
Quite simple, get yourselfadopted as a candidate,
赢得普选 再做后座议员
win a general election,serve on the back benches,
最后当上大臣 撤销法案 没问题
become a Ministerand repeal the act.
就是獾们等不了你
The badgers might begetting on a bit by then.
助理秘书直接向大臣报告?
Assistant Secretariesreporting to the Minister!
我明白
I know.
他以为他是谁?公务员吗?
Does he thinkhe is a civil servant?
政客都是自大狂
The arroganceof these politicians!
啊 伯纳
Ah, Bernard.
谢谢
Thank you.
好
Yes.
非常好
Fine.
最后这份可以给大臣看 伯纳
You can show that last oneto the Minister.
他会安静好一会的
He'll be quiet fora bit.
还有事吗 伯纳?
Is something the matter?
这个 只是...
Well, it's just that...
我越来越担心
I've been increasinglyworried about
把事情瞒着大臣
keeping things backfrom the Minister.
我先失陪...      不用不用
Shall I...No, no, no.
你是什么意思?
What do you mean?
如果他想了解情况 为什么不告诉他?
Why shouldn't he be allowedto know things ifhe wants to?
傻小子
Silly Boy!
伯纳 我国政府的运作方式在于
Bernard, this country is governedby Ministers making decisions
大臣从我们提供的方案中
from the variousalternative proposals
遴选决策 对吧?      对啊
thatwe offerthem, is it not?Oh, yes.
所以
Well...
如果他们掌握了事实
If they had all the facts,
他们会看到其它可能性
they'd see all sortsof otherpossibilities.
甚至会自己提出方案来
They might even formulatetheirown plans
而不从我们那两三个方案里选
instead of choosing betweenthe ones thatwe put up.
那不行吗?      那不行吗!
Would that matter?Would it matter!
可是为什么?
But why?
由我们自己来编写提案
As long as we can formulateourown proposals, we can
能引导他们作出正确决策
guide themto the correct decision.
能吗?怎么引导?
Can we? How?
就像变戏法
It's like a conjuror.
"三张牌"魔术
The Three Card Trick.
随便挑一张 最后总挑中你要的那张
"Take any card", they pickthe one that you intend.
我们这个叫"四字诀"
Ours is the fourword trick.
有四个词能让大臣采纳提案
There are fourwords if you wanta Ministerto accept a proposal.
快捷 简单 时兴 便宜
Quick. Simple. Popular. Cheap.
还有四个词 能让提案
And there are fourwordsfora proposal
被大臣否决
if you want it thrown out.
复杂 耗时 昂贵 争议
Complicated. Lengthy.Expensive. Controversial.
要彻底排除大臣采纳的可能性
And to be really surethe Ministerdoesn't accept it,
就得说这决定"有魄力"
you say the decisionis courageous.
比"争议"还惨?
Worse than "controversial".
"争议"只表示"会失去部分选票"
"Controversial" means"this'll lose yourvotes".
"魄力"表示"会失掉整个大选"
"Courageous" means"this will lose you the election".
你看 如果他们掌握的不是选项而是事实
You see, if they have all the factsinstead of just the options
他们可要自己动脑子了
they might start thinkingforthemselves!
这个体制有用?      有用?
And the system works?Works?
这是今日英国的基石
It's made Britainwhat she is today.
哦 对 我明白了
Oh, yes. I see. Yes.
你那位怎样 小汉?      我给他一堆文件看
What about yourman?I'm giving him plenty to read.
你不该向他挑明
Shouldn't you showhim
无知有时候也是一种美德么?
the positive virtuesofbeing kept ignorant?
要是他从政20年连这都不懂...
Lfhe doesn't know thatafter 20 years as a politician...
有问题吗 伯纳?      是的 公文盒里有封信
You look worried, Bernard.I've just found this letter.
怎么?      不知道该不该拆
I don't knowif I should open it.
你知道规定
You know the rules.
私人秘书可以拆阅各级机密 包括顶极
Private secretaries shall openall classifications up to Top Secret.
只有标"亲启"的不能拆
Only letters marked "personal"shall remain unopened,
除非大臣另作指示
unless the Ministerorders otherwise.
那"爸爸"呢?
What about Daddy?
我不知道这和你父亲有何关系
Where does yourfathercome into this?
不是 写着"爸爸收""紧急"
No. To "Daddy". "Urgent".
写了"亲启"没有?      没
Does it say"Personal"?No.
按照规定 那就得拆了
Well then, it must be opened.
是大臣的女儿写的      真没料到
It's from the Minister's daughter.You astound me.
后院起火啦?
Trouble at the mill.
哈克小姐要参加护獾运动
Miss Hackerwill jointhe badgerprotest.
不是结束了嘛      她和她男朋友发起的
I thought itwas over.She and herboyfriend.
在海华树林 24小时"拯救獾群"抗议
A 24 hour"Save the badgers"vigil in Hayward's Spinney
直到恢复保护区
unless protection is restored.
他们下午5点通报媒体
And they announcing itto the press at 5.00 p.m.
"大臣之女抗议屠獾"
"Minister's daughterin badgerprotest vigil".
有点尴尬 不太严重
A little embarrassing,but not too serious.
汉弗莱爵士 大臣可能不止有点尴尬
The Ministerwill bemore than a little embarrassed.
怎么?      "大臣之女裸体抗议屠獾"
"Minister's daughter in nudebadgerprotest vigil".
什么
What!
对 哈克小姐和她男朋友会...
Miss Hackerand herboyfriend will be...
也就是说 他们不会...
that is, will not not be...I mean...
他们要脱光 伯纳?      对 汉弗莱爵士
Do you mean starkers, Bernard?Yes, Sir Humphrey.
那就麻烦了      特别是这么冷的天
A different complexion on it.Especially in this weather.
按记者的话说 这叫特大新闻
Put in crude journalistic terms,this makes it a big story.
头版 附照片
Front page: with photograph.
你好啊 汉弗莱
Hello, Humphrey.
有什么事么?
Something the matter?
什么?
Well?
有件小事 比较尴尬 大臣
Shall we say a slightembarrassment, Minister?
多小的事?
How slight?
即使尽量避免夸大事实
Withoutwishing in any senseto overstate the case
或者危言耸听 状况仍然...
orcause undue alarm,nevertheless, the fact remains...
得了 汉弗莱 说吧
Come on! Outwith it.
大臣 我要坦白一件事      这倒新鲜
I have a confession to make.That's a change.
说吧 汉弗莱 敞开胸怀吧
Well, come on, Humphrey,make a clean breast of it.
最好不要这么形容 大臣
Not the happiest of phrasesunderthe circumstances.
怎么讲?
How do you mean?
我必须承认 獾群危机
I have to confessthat the badgers
比我们预想的要大
may be a somewhat biggerstorythan we thought.
别告诉我獾要下崽了
Don't tell methey're going to have kittens.
问题不在獾的崽子 大臣
It is not the badgerswho are going to have kittens.
海华树林会有个24小时抗议
There'll be a 24 hourprotest vigilin Hayward's Spinney.
你说那不算新闻      这回不太一样
Thatwouldn't be newsworthy.This is slightly different.
参加者包括
It's to be conducted...
一名女学生及其男友
by a girl studentand herboyfriend.
就他们两个?      对
Just the two of them?Yes.
谁管他们 一对闲人
They don't matter.A pairof layabouts.
有些人可能非管不可      胡说 伯纳
They might matterto some people.Nonsense.
这些学生只想露露脸
These students arejust exhibitionists.
这回露的可不止是脸
In this case they havesomething to exhibit.
怎么讲?      他们要裸体抗议
How do you mean?It's to be a nude protest vigil.
是这样
I see.
会上头版的      可不是
Thatwould make the front pages!Yes, quite so.
不能让媒体知道
The press just mustn't find out.
真不明白这些学生什么毛病
I don't knowwhat gets into these students.
真可怕 不要脸      确实 大臣
It's appalling. They're shameless.Indeed, Minister.
你知道 都是家长的错
It's theirparents.
父母养而不教
They don't bring them upproperly.
由他们撒野 给他们
Just let them run wildand feed them
灌输些反社会思想
all this antiestablishmentnonsense.
也许不全是家长的错
Perhaps it isn't entirelythe parents fault.
当然是家长的错
Of course it is!
威信啊 汉弗莱
Authority, Humphrey.
看这些学生就知道
All this is an indictment
父母不懂管教和纪律
of theirparent's lackof discipline.
导致孩子坑害无辜的人 比如我
So they just take it outon innocent people like me.
他们是谁?      知道那位小姐的名字
Who are they?We know the young lady's name.
还小姐呢 是谁?
Lady!Who is she?
她似乎叫哈克小姐
It seems she's a Miss Hacker.
哈克...哦 跟我一样
Hacker... oh, that's my name.
还真巧
That's a coincidence.
不完全是巧合
Not a complete coincidence.
不是...露西吧?
Not... not Lucy?
我的天呐
Oh, my God!
您看 她10分钟之内会来电话
She will be telephoningin ten minutes time.
也许媒体不感兴趣?没指望的...
Perhaps the press won't beall that interested? No, no...
媒体真会跑去沃里克郡?
Butwill they go all the wayup to Warwickshire?
为这种故事
Fora story like this,
恐怕他们不惜一路跑到南极
they'll go all the wayto the South Pole.
这可不能上报 提建议啊 汉弗莱
This story must be killed.Advise me, Humphrey.
大臣 管教管教如何?
What abouta little parental discipline?
别傻了
Don't be silly.
也许可以让她服理      她是学社会学的 伯纳
Make her listen to reason.She's a sociology student.
让您夫人把她锁起来?
Perhaps Mrs. Hackercould lock her in herroom?
安妮出差去了 报警如何?
Annie's out atwork.What about the police?
"大臣报警镇压裸体女儿"
"Ministersets policeon nude daughter".
这故事也差不了多少 大臣
I'm not sure that completelykills the story.
一定有办法      等我看看档案...
There must be something.Perhaps if I look at the files...
好呀 我女儿就要上《太阳报》头版了
My daughter's about to getpage one of the Sun,
大概还要上第三版 你就知道看文件
and probably page three,and you just think of the files.
不过...      都在外面
Nevertheless...They're all out there.
会以什么角度报导呢?      广角镜头
What angle they'll take?Wide angle.
反对党该高兴了
Oppositionwill have fun with this.
"英雄之父有何感言?"
"Does the proud fatherwish to make a statement?".
"哈克一家急于曝光?"
"Is the Hackerfamily gettingtoo much exposure?".
"大臣会掩盖起来吗?"
"Is the Ministertryingto conduct a coverup?".
"一家不治 何以治部?"
"Does he run his Departmentbetterthan his family?".
你要我说是汉弗莱在治理这个部?
You'd like me to tell themthat Humphrey runs it?
当然不会 大臣 我是您的私人秘书
No, of course not.I am your Private Secretary.
你是说 每到紧急时刻
Do you meanthat when the chips are down,
你站我这边 不是汉弗莱那边?
you're on my side,not Humphrey's?
大臣 我的工作就是避免这种紧急时刻
Minister, it's my job to seethe chips stay up.
喂?
Hello?
请找哈克先生 我是他女儿
Can I speak to Mr. Hacker?It's his daughter.
找您的 大臣
It's foryou, Minister.
露西 你好 亲爱的
Lucy. Hello, darling.
你好 爸爸      我收到信了
Hello, Daddy.I got yournote.
吓我一跳 还以为你当真的呢
Fora momentI thought itwas serious.
是当真的 性命攸观
It is serious.It's deadly serious.
彼得和我马上通报媒体
Pete and I are just goingto ring the press,
然后去树林
then we're off to the Spinney.
千万别 想想后果啊
Don't do that!Think of the damage.
什么后果?
What damage?
这个...会损害我
Well... to me.
你?果然如此
To you? Isn't that typical?
对獾的损害又怎么说?
What about damageto badgers?
你又不会被消灭
You're not goingto be exterminated.
从某种意义上说 是的
Well, in a sense, yes.
那好 你知道该怎么做了
Then you knowwhat to do.
10秒...      等等 等等
Ten...Look... Look...
9...      露西 别
Nine...Lucy, don't...
8...      露西
Eight...Lucy!
大臣 请让我和小姐说句话
If I could have a wordwith the young lady.
汉弗莱・阿普比爵士有话要说      有新进展
Sir Humphrey Applebywants a word with you.
有新进展      6...5...
A new development.Six... five...
哈克小姐 您好吗?
Miss Hacker...Ah, how do you do?
我是汉弗莱・阿普比
Humphrey Appleby here.
哈克先生的常任秘书      还有5秒
Mr. Hacker's Permanent Secretary.Five and holding.
请听我说一句 小姐
If I could just have a word.
我刚看到政府
I have just seen the latest report
督察员最新报告
from the Government's inspectors,
这件事又有新进展
which throws new lighton the issue.
怎么?
Why?
显然树林里并没有獾群
Apparently there isno badgercolony in Spinney.
报告中写道
Now, it says here
"最后一次发现獾的粪便和洞穴"
"Last evidence ofbadgerdroppings, freshly turned earth
"是在11年前"
was recordedeleven years ago".
可报纸上...
But the papers...
显然那篇报导是地产商炮制的
Apparently the story was fedto them by a property developer.
地产商?      显然 市政厅计划
Property developer?Yes. The Council has plans
用树林修建成人教育学院
to use the spinneyfora new Collegeof Further Education,
而地产商想建写字楼和高级公寓
and the developerwants itforoffices and luxuryflats.
可如果被保护着 他也用不了
Well, if it's protectedhe won't be able to.
市政厅也用不了
And, norwill the Council.
他盘算好市政厅会把经费转走
And he knows they'll usethe moneyforsomething else,
一年之后他再宣传根本没有獾
then he can establishthat there's no badgercolony,
取消保护区 兴建写字楼
get the protection orderremovedand build his offices.
这都是司空见惯了
It's common practice.
就是说树林里根本没有野生动物?
So there isn't any wildlifein the spinney at all?
有倒是有 那里被伍顿沃文地区
Well, there is some.It's been used as a rubbish dump
用作垃圾场 所以耗子不少
by people from Wootton Wawen,so there're lots of rats.
耗子?      对 不下几千只
Rats?Yes. Several thousand, actually.
怎么说它们也算野生动物吧?
They are wildlife too,in theirway, aren't they?
便宜了地产商就可惜了
Itwould be a pity to playinto the developer's hands.
对 我同意
Yes, I suppose itwould.
我非常敬佩您的远见和献身精神
Yes, I very much respectyourviews and yourcommitment.
还要找大臣说话吗?
Would you like to speakto the Minister?
不 不用了 算了吧
No, that's all right.Oh, well. Forget it then.
汉弗莱 我诚心向你道歉
Humphrey!I take it all back!
没什么 大臣 都写在档案里
Itwas nothing, Minister.Itwas all in the files.
地产商
A property developer!
这些奸商...给我看看文件
The cunning devils...Let me look at the file!
大臣 您不会感兴趣的
I don't thinkyou'd find them interesting.
给我看看      不 我认为您还是...
Let me have a look.No, I don't think you'd...
汉弗莱
Humphrey!
你说的是真的吧?
Itwas true, wasn't it?
汉弗莱 你给露西讲的那一套里
Was there one word of truthin that whole story
有一句真话么?
you told to Lucy?
大臣 您真想要我回答?
Do you really want meto answerthat question?
不 我...
No.
还是算了      正是
I don't think I do.Quite so.
也许某些事情 大臣还是不知道的好
Perhaps there're some thingsit is betterfora Ministernot to know.